Chapter 108. Ahab and the Carpenter.
The deck. First night watch. Carpenter standing before his vice bench, and by
the light of two lanterns, busily filing the ivory joist for the leg, which joist
is firmly fixed in the vice. slabs of ivory, leather straps, pads, screws, and
various tools of all sorts lying about the bench. Forward the red flame of the
forge is seen, where the blacksmith is at work.
Drat the file, and drought the bone.
That is hard, which should be soft, and that is soft, which should be hard. So
we go, who file old jaws and shin bones.
Let's try another. Ah, now this works better. Sneezes.
Hello. This bone dust is sneezes. Why, it's sneezes. Yes, it's sneezes. Bless
my soul. It won't let me speak. That is what an old fellow gets now for working
in dead lumber. Saw a live tree and you don't get this dust. Amputate a live
bone and you don't get it. Sneezes.
Come, come, you old smut. There, bear a hand and let's have that feral and
buckle screw. I'll be ready for them presently.
Lucky now, sneezes. There's no knee joint to make. That might puzzle a
little. But a mere shin bone. Why, it's as easy as making hop poles. Only I
should like to put a good finish on.
Time. Time. If I but only had the time, I could turn him out as needle leg now
as ever, sneezes, scraped to a lady in a parlor. Those buckskin legs and calves
of legs I've seen in shop windows wouldn't compare at all. They soak water
they do and of course get rumatic and have to be doctorred sneezes with washes
and lotions just like live legs. Fair.
before I saw it off. Now I must call his old mogul ship and see whether the
length will be all right. Too short if anything, I guess. Ha, that's the heel.
We are in luck. Here he comes. Or at somebody else, that's certain. Ahab
advancing. During the ensuing scene, the carpenter continues sneezing at times.
Well, man maker, just in time, sir.
If the captain pleases, I will now mark the length. Let me measure, sir.
Measured for a leg. Good. Well, it's not the first time. About it. There. Keep
thy finger on it. This is a cogent vice thou hast here, carpenter. Let me feel
its grip once. So, so it does pinch some. Oh, sir, it will break bones.
Beware. Beware. No fear. I like a good grip. I like to feel something in this
slippery world that can hold man.
What's Prometheus about there? The blacksmith. I mean, what's he about? He
must be forging the buckle screw, sir.
Now, right. It's a partnership. He supplies the muscle part. He makes a
fierce red flame there. I sir, he must have the white heat for this kind of fine work.
So he must I do deem it now a most meaning thing that this old Greek
Prometheus who made men they say should have been a blacksmith and animated them
with fire. For what's made in fire must properly belong to fire and so hell's
probable. How the soot flies. This must be the remainder the Greek made the
Africans of. Carpenter, when he's through with that buckle, tell him to
forge a pair of steel shoulder blades.
There is a peddler aboard with a crushing pack.
Sir, hold. While Prometheus is about it, I'll order a complete man after a
desirable pattern. Impremis 50 feet high in his socks. Then chest modeled after
the temp's tunnel. Then legs with roots to him to stay in one place. Then arms
three feet through the wrist. No heart at all. Brass forehead and about a
quarter of an acre of fine brains. And let me see. Shall I order eyes to see
outwards? No, but put a skylight on top of his head to illuminate inwards.
There, take the order and away.
Now, what's he speaking about and who is he speaking to? I should like to know.
Uh, shall I keep standing here? Aside.
It is but in different architecture to make a blind dome. Here's one. No, no,
no. I must have a lantern. Ho ho. That's it. Eh, here are two, sir. Uh, one will
serve my turn.
What art thou thrusting that thief catcher into my face for, man? Thrusted
light is worse than presented pistols.
I thought, sir, that you spoke to Carpenter. Carpenter? Why, that's But
no, a very tidy, and I may say an extremely gentlemanlike sort of business
thou art in here, Carpenter. Or would thou rather work in clay, sir? Clay? Uh,
clay, sir? That's mud. We We leave clay to ditchers, sir. The fellow's impious.
What art thou sneezing about? A bone is rather dusty, sir. Take the hint, then.
And when thou art dead, never bury thyself under living people's noses,
sir. Oh, uh, uh, I guess so. Uh, yes, dear. Look, carpenter, I dare say thou
callest thyself a right good workmanlike workman, eh? Well then, will it speak
thoroughly well for thy work? If, when I come to mount this leg, thou makest, I
shall nevertheless feel another leg in the same identical place with it. That
is, carpenter my old lost leg, the flesh and blood one, I mean. Can thou not
drive that old Adam away?
Truly, sir, I begin to understand somewhat now. Yes, I have heard
something curious on that score, sir, how a dismastered man never entirely
loses the feeling of his old spar, but it will be still pricking him at times.
May I humbly ask if it really be so, sir? It is, man. Look, put thy live leg
here in the place where mine once was.
So now here is only one distinct leg to the eye, yet two to the soul. Where thou
feelest tingling life, there exactly there, there to a hair do I? Is it a
riddle? I should humbly call it a poser, sir. H then how dust thou know that some
entire living thinking thing may not be invisibly and uninterpenetratingly
standing precisely where thou now standest? I and standing there in thy
spite in thy most solitary hours then dust thou not fear eavesdroppers?
Hold. Don't speak. And if I still feel the smart of my crushed leg, though it
be now so long dissolved, then why mayest not thou carpenter feel the fiery
pains of hell forever and without a body? Huh?
Good lord. Truly, sir, if it comes to that, I must calculate over again. I
think I didn't carry a small figure, sir. Look ye, Pudding Head should never
grant premises. How long before the leg is done? Perhaps an hour, sir. Bungle
away at it then, and bring it to me.
Turns to go.
Oh, life. Here I am, proud as a Greek god, and yet standing dead to this
blockhead for a bone to stand on. Cursed be that mortal interend indebtedness,
which will not do away with ledgers. I would be free as heir and I'm down in
the whole world's books. I am so rich I could have given bid for bid with the
wealthiest Ptorians at the auction of the Roman Empire which was the worlds.
And yet I owe for the flesh in the tongue I brag with. By heavens I'll get
a crucible and into it and dissolve myself down to one small compendious vertebra.
So Carpenter resuming his work. Well, well, well. Stub knows him best of all. And
Stub always says he's queer. Says nothing but that one sufficient little
word. Queer. He's queer, says Stub. He's queer. Queer. Queer. And keeps dinning
it into Mr. Starbucks all the time.
Queer, sir. Queer. Queer. very queer.
And here's his leg. Yes, now that I think of it, here's his bed fellow. He
has a stick of whales jawbone for a wife. And this is his leg. He'll stand
on this. What was that now about one leg standing in three places, and all the
three places standing in one hell? How was that? Oh, I don't wonder. He looked
so scornful at me. I'm a sort of strangethoughted sometimes, they say.
But that's only halfhazardlike.
Then a short little old body like me should never undertake to wade out into
deep waters with tall heron-built captains. The water chucks you under the
chin pretty quick. And there's a great cry for lifeboats. And here's the
heron's leg. Long and slim, sure enough.
Now, for most folks, one pair of legs lasts a lifetime. And that must be
because they use them mercifully as a tender-hearted old lady uses her roly
pololy old coach horses. But Ahab, oh, he's a hard driver. Look, driven one leg
to death and spaven the other for life and now wears out bone legs by the cord.
Hello there, you smut. Bear a hand there with those screws and let's finish it
before the resurrection fellow comes a calling with his horn for all legs, true
or false, as brewery men go around collecting old beer barrels to fill them
up again. What a leg this is. It looks like a real live leg filed down to
nothing but the core. He'll be standing on this tomorrow. He'll be taking
altitudes on it. Hello. I almost forgot the little oval slate, smoothed ivory
where he figures up the latitude. So, so chisel, file, and sandpaper now.